Guide to the Pettigrew Papers
Yale University Library
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection
Pettigrew papers
1797-1865
Pettigrew, Thomas Joseph, 1791-1865.
OSB MSS 113
Total Boxes: 21
Linear Feet: 7.09
The collection consists of letters to Pettigrew from a variety of correspondents, including scholars and antiquarians, members of the nobility and gentry, and professional colleagues. The letters concern scientific matters, including Egyptology and medicine, and the affairs of the various learned societies of which Pettigrew was a member, such as the British Archaeological Association, the Medical Society of London, the Royal Society, the Society of Antiquarians, and the Archaeologcal Institute of Great Britain and Ireland. A few letters concern the Duke of Sussex.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library P. O. Box 208240 New Haven, CT 06520-8240 Email: beinecke.library@yale.edu Phone: (203) 432-2972 Fax: (203) 432-4047
Administrative Information
Provenance
Purchased in 1971 from Winifred A. Myers, Ltd. on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Fund.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
THOMAS JOSEPH PETTIGREW, 1791-1865
Thomas Joseph Pettigrew, second son of the surgeon-apothecary William Pettigrew, was born in London on October 28th, 1791. After serving his apprenticeship under the surgeon John Taunton, he was elected secretary of the Medical Society of London in 1812, became secretary to the Royal Humane Society in the following year, and was subsequently appointed surgeon to the Duke of Kent
Pettigrew was appointed surgeon and librarian to the Duke of Sussex in 1819, and in the following two decades successfully pursued a dual career as surgeon and as antiquary. He became surgeon to the Asylum for Female Orphans and to the Charing Cross Hospital, and he was elected fellow of the Royal Society. In his role as librarian, Pettigrew planned an ambitious catalogue of the Duke of Sussex's collection, the first volume of which was published in 1827 as Bibliotheca Sussexiana.
During the 1830s, however, Pettigrew faced difficulties in both of his chosen fields. The Duke of Sussex, embarrassed by Pettigrew's tendencies to gossip and by his mismanagement of the Duke's 1830 election as President of the Royal Society, dismissed him from his posts. In 1835, Pettigrew resigned from Charing Cross Hospital in the wake of accusations that he had accepted fees from candidates for assistant surgeons' appointments.
Although he published a spirited defense of his conduct, Pettigrew withdrew to private medical practice and devoted increasing time to his antiquarian interests. He published A History of Egyptian Mummies in 1834 and the first part of his planned Encyclopaedia Aegyptiana (never completed) in 1842. While Sussex refused to reinstate him as his librarian, he did allow Pettigrew to complete and publish the second volume of of his planned Bibliotheca Sussexiana in 1834. Pettigrew's four volume Medical Portrait Gallery, which included his own biographical sketch, appeared in 1839.
In 1843 Pettgrew was elected as fellow to the Royal College of Surgeons, and in the same year became one of the founding members of the British Archaeological Association, serving as its treasurer for the rest of his life. He was also active in the Percy Society, the Historical Society of Science, and the Society of Antiquaries, and authored many antiquarian articles for the Journal of the British Archaeological Association and Archaeologica.
During the early 1850s Pettigrew again engaged in controversies, publishing an attack on the management of the Society of Antiquaries in 1852 (Letter to the Lord Viscount Mahon) and defending his own management of the British Archaelogical Association from an attack by Richard Hugo in 1854. In that year his wife died, and Pettigrew retired from medical practice entirely. He published Chronicles of the Tombs in 1857. Thomas Pettigrew died at home in Brompton on November 23, 1865. His library was sold at Sotheby's seven months later.
Description of the Papers
The Pettigrew Papers consist almost entirely of letters received by Thomas Pettigrew. The papers span the dates 1791-1865 and are organized into two series: General Correspondence Files and Additional Correspondence.
Series I, General Correspondence Files, is housed in Boxes 1-13 and is arranged alphabetically by author. Detailed folder notes in the box and folder list highlight the main topics of most correspondents' letters. In general, the bulk of the correspondences deals with routine business matters of the British Archaeological Association, and includes responses to requests for donations and support; nominations to various offices; meeting and tour arrangements; papers and publications by members; and the general antiquarian interests of the correspondents. There is also considerable discussion of the competition between the B.A.A. and other antiquarian organizations, particularly the Archaeological Institute and the Society of Antiquaries, as well as commentary on the internal politics of all of the associations.
Pettigrew's tireless promotion of the British Archaeological Association is perhaps best illustrated by his extensive correspondence with members of the nobility and gentry whose patronage he solicited. His results were mixed. For example, the Marquess of Camden declined the Presidency, but accepted a largely ceremonial Vice-Presidency; several nobles, including the Dukes of Devonshire and Grafton and the Earl of Ferrers, declined the Vice-Presidencies as well. Baron Berwick agreed to be listed as a patron provided that he would not be asked to "perform any active part in matters which I do not at all understand," while Baron Stanley accepted a Vice-Presidency on the condition that he would not be required to attend meetings. Many correspondents declined altogether. On the other hand, Baron Londesborough's letters discuss his work for the organization in great detail (Box 7, folders 346-347)
Nevertheless, several noble correspondents became active members of the BAA: the letters of the Earl of Darnley (Box 4, folder 162) and of the Earl of Arundell (Box 1, folder 21) document visits by the society to their estates, while those of the Earl of Harrowby describe an antiquarian article intended for the BAA's quarterly periodical. Baron Londesborough's many letters discuss his work for the organization in great detail (Box 7, folders 346-347).
Box 21 contains a few personal papers, including a photograph of Pettigrew and a prospectus for the restoration of Shakespeare's tomb.
Access Terms
This collection is indexed under the following access points in Orbis, the Yale University Library online catalog.
Subjects
Beattie, William, 1793-1875.; Betham, William, Sir, 1779-1853.; Brodie, Benjamin, Sir, 1783-1862.; Carlisle, Nicholas, 1771-1847.; Cooper, Astley, Sir, 1768-1841.; Ellis, Henry, Sir, 1777-1869.; Lee, John, 1783-1866.; Londesborough, Albert Denison, Baron, 1805-1860.; Meyrick, Samuel Rush, Sir, 1783-1848.; Pettigrew, Thomas Joseph, 1791-1865.; Planché, J. R. (James Robinson), 1796-1880.; Smyth, W. H. (William Henry), 1788-1865.; Westmacott, Richard, Sir.; Wilkinson, John Gardner, Sir, 1797-1875.; British Archaeological Association.; Medical Society of London.; Royal Society (Great Britain); Society of Antiquaries of London.; Egyptology.; Learning and scholarship --Great Britain.; Medicine --Manuscripts.
Authors
Pettigrew, Thomas Joseph, 1791-1865.
Collection Contents
- General Correspondence Files, 1797-1865; Series I:; 4.59' (13 boxes)
  Series I, General Correspondence Files, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - [Provenance documents and biographical sources] (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Aberdeen, George Hamilton-Gordon, 4th Earl of, 1784-1860. 1 ALS, 1 LS, 1 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1846 Aug (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letter deals with a forthcoming election within the Society of Antiquaries.
  - Abingdon, Montagu Bertie, 6th Earl of, 1808-1884. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1859, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Acland, Sir Thomas Dyke, bart., 1787-1871. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Agrees to be a Vice President of the British Archaeological Association
  - Aikin, Arthur, 1773-1854. 3 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1823-30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letters discuss the Society of Arts.
  - Ailesbury, George William Frederick Brudnell-Bruce, 2d Marquess of, 1804-1878. 5 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1858-59 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Letters concern the British Archaeological Association and Ailesbury's connection with it and his selection as President.
  - Ainslie, Sir Whitelaw, 1767-1837. 1 ALS and 2 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1828 Jun (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ainsworth, William Francis, 1807-1896. 5 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1843-56 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ainsworth, William Harrison, 1805-1882. 5 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1854-60 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Akerman, John Yonge, 1806-1873. 9 ALS and 2 LS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1849-56 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letters discuss minor details of the Antiquarian Society and some of Pettigrew's contributions.
  - Albemarle, Charlotte (Hunloke) Keppel, Countess of, d. 1862. AL to Mr. Stephenson, 1822 Mar 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Written one month after her marriage to Albemarle.
  - Albemarle, George Thomas Keppel, 6th Earl of, 1799-1891. 4 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1857 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Letters concern Albemarle's association with the British Archaeological Association. He has been asked to preside over one of its meetings.
  - Alcock, Thomas, 1784-1833. 3 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1830-33 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Amyot, Thomas, 1775-1850. 6 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1827 and later (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Letters discuss an apparent feud within the British Archaeological Association. Lord Conyngham is mentioned.
  - Anderson, Joseph, 1789-1877. 3 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1843-47 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Letters discuss medical matters. Pettigrew was apparently Anderson's personal physician.
  - Anglo-Biblical Institute. ALS (signed W. H. Clarke) to T. J. Pettigrew, 1859 Nov 28 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Seeks information concerning the Duke of Sussex.
  - Arran, Mary (Tyrrell), Countess, 1767?-1832. AL to Augustus Frederick, Duke of Sussex, [1824 or later] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Arundale, Francis, 1807-1853. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Arundell, Henry Benedict Arundell, 11th Baron, 1804-1862. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1852 Jun-Sep (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Letters discuss a visit to Wardour Castle by the British Archaeological Association and the subsequent enrollment of Arundell as a member.
  - Arundell, John Francis Arundell, 12th Baron, 1831-1906. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1860 Mar (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Letters discuss Arundell's membership in the British Archaeological Association and a request for information concerning the siege of Wardour Castle by Edward Hungerford in 1643.
  - Ashburton, Alexander Baring, 1st Baron, 1774-1848. 2 ALS to T.J. Pettigrew., [1839 or later] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Letter thanks Pettigrew for a copy of one of his works.
  - Ashburton, William Bingham Baring, 2d Baron, 1799-1864. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ashpitel, Arthur, 1807-1869. 3 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1850 Aug (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Auckland, George Eden, 1st Earl of, 1784-1849. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1828 Dec 7 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Auckland, Robert John Eden, 3d Baron, Bp. of Bath and Wells, 1799-1870. 6 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1856-59 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Letters discuss Auckland's affiliations with the British Archaeological Association. A second letter dismisses Pettigrew's suit that his son be presented to a living.
  - Ayrton, William, 1777-1858. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1827 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Letter discusses Pettigrew's election to the Royal Society.
  - Babington, Benjamin Guy, 1794-1866. 3 ALS and 1 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1830-38 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    One letter marked "Private" expresses Babington's intention to vote for the Duke of Sussex for President of the Royal Society. Other letters discuss Pettigrew's works on mummies and his Medical Portrait Gallery.
  - Babington, William, 1756-1833. AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1817 Jun 6 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Letter mentions Philosophical Society of London.
  - Baird, [William?], 1803-1872. 2 ALS and 3 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1831-34 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Agrees to subscribe to Pettigrew's work on mummies.
  - Banks, Thomas Christopher, 1765-1854. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1845 Jun 30 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Baring, Charles, Bp. of Durham, 1807-1879. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, [1850]-1865 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Baring, Sir Thomas, 1772-1848. AL to Mr. Stephenson, 1831 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Baron, John, 1786-1851. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, [1836 or later] (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Barrington, William Keppel Barrington, 6th Viscount, 1793-1867. AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1834 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Letter discusses a charity case.
  - Bateman, Thomas, 1821-1861. 4 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1850-52 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Letters discuss Egyptian antiquities, places of archaeological interest in England, and a congress of the British Archaeological Association.
  - Bateman, William Bateman Bateman-Hanbury, 2d Baron, 1826-1901. ALS and 1 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1857, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Beattie, William, 1793-1875. 15 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1829-[36] (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Letters discuss some medical matters and the British Archaeological Association
  - Beaufort, Emily Frances (Smith), Duchess of, 1800?-1889. AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1829 Jul 31 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Gives Pettigrew proxy votes for selecting members of the School for the Indigent Blind.
  - Beaufort, Sir Francis, 1774-1857. ALS to Sir Gardner Wilkinson, 1850 Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Beaufort, Henry Charles Fitzroy Somerset, 8th Duke of, 1824-1899. ALS and AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1854 Jul, Oct (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Declines to become a member of the British Archaeological Association.
  - Beaumont, Sir George Howland, bart., 1753-1827. AL to Lord Ferrers (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bedford, John Russell, 6th Duke of, 1766-1839. 3 ALS and 1 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1827-34 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Letters comment upon the Duke of Sussex's Library and Pettigrew's Bibliotheca Sussexiana.
  - Bell, Robert, 1800-1867. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1857 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Bell, Thomas, 1792-1880. 3 ALS and 2 LS to T. J. Pettigrew, [1834]-53 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Bell agrees to subscribe to several of Pettigrew's works. One letter acknowledges receipt of two gifts from Pettigrew, on behalf of the Royal Society.
  - Beltz, George Frederick, 1777-1841. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1829 Mar 5 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Bernal, Ralph, d. 1854. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1853 Nov 10 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Letter concerns the presentation by Mr. Delaborde of two of his works to the British Archaeological Association
  - Berry, William, 1774-1851. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1831 Apr, Jun (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Berry seeks permission to make drawings of some heraldic robes and also seeks the patronage of the Duke of Sussex.
  - Berwick, Richard Noel Noel-Hill, 5th Baron, 1800-1861. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1860 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Allows his name to be used by the British Archaeological Association as long as he is not required to perform "any active part in ... matters which I do not at all understand."
  - Betham, Sir William, 1779-1853. 22 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1826-52 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    On Betham's work for the Royal Irish Academy, the formation of the Archaeological Inst. of Gt. Brit. and the Brit. Arch. Assoc. and their founders. Some letters discuss in detail several of Betham's papers.
  - Billing, Archibald, 1791-1881. 2 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1828 Jun (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Birkbeck, George, 1776-1841. 10 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1821-37 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Many letters discuss the Mechanics Institution and various attempts by Birbeck to enlist the support of the Duke of Sussex. Several letters also attempt to gain support for his son's election to the Athenaeum.
  - Blaauw, William Henry, 1793-1870. 2 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Black, William Henry, 1808-1872. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1849 Feb 28 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Discusses the Whitechapel Rectory Bill in Parliament.
  - Blane, Sir Gilbert, bart., 1749-1834. ALS and AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1827 Nov (Box 2, Folder 56)
    Blane presents two of his works to the Duke of Sussex.
  - Blessington, Charles John Gardiner, 2d Earl of, 1782-1829. 6 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, [1820]-26 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    Some of the letters mention the death of "Mr. [John] Scott."
  - Blessington, Margaret (Power) Farmer Gardiner, Countess of, 1789-1849. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1821-[35] (Box 2, Folder 58)
    Letters discuss Mrs. Pettigrew's health and an attempt by Pettigrew to find a job for his son.
  - Blundell, James, 1790-1877. 6 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, [1833]-38 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Letters discuss medical matters and treatments. One letter discusses Pettigrew's Medical Portrait Gallery.
  - Bolland, Sir William, 1772-1840. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1827 Mar 26 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Bonney, Henry Kaye, 1780-1862. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1852 Aug (Box 2, Folder 61)
    Letters discuss the arrangements for a visit to Lincoln by the British Archaeological Association.
  - Bonomi, Joseph, 1796-1878. 4 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, and 1 calling card., 1845-57 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    One letter discusses Egyptian hieroglyphs.
  - Boston, George Ives Irby, 4th Baron, 1802-1869. 6 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, [1857-62] (Box 2, Folder 63)
    Letters mention Boston's affiliation with the British Archaeological Association.
  - Bowers, George Hull, 1794-1872. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1850 May (Box 2, Folder 64)
    Letter mentions a visit by the British Archaeological Association to Manchester Cathedral.
  - Boyd, Sir William. 4 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1843-[54] (Box 2, Folder 65)
    Discuss Boyd's and Pettigrew's works and indicate that Boyd offered a series of lectures on modern literature for which he sought Pettigrew's aid.
  - Boyne, Gustavus Frederick John James Hamilton-Russell, 7th viscount, 1797-1872. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1860, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    Letters discuss Boyne's affiliation with the British Archaeological Association.
  - Brande, William Thomas, 1788-1866. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, [1806 or later] (Box 2, Folder 67)
    Brande accepts an honor bestowed on him by the Philosophical Society of London.
  - Braybrooke, Charles Cornwallis Neville, 5th Baron, 1823-1902. 2 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1861, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    Declines an invitation to subscribe to the British Archaeological Assn.
  - Braybrooke, Richard Cornwallis Neville, 4th Baron, 1820-1861. 4 ALS and 1 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1859 Jul (Box 2, Folder 69)
    Letters mention the activities of the British Archaeological Assn.
  - Braybrooke, Richard Griffin, 2d Baron, 1750-1825. ALS (fragment) to T. J. Pettigrew, 1804 Mar 23 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Breadalbane, John Campbell, 2d Marquis of, 1796-1862. AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1833 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Bree, Robert, 1759-1839. ALS and AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1838 Apr (Box 2, Folder 72)
    Bree offers to subscribe to Pettigrew's Medical Portrait Gallery.
  - Brenton, Edward Pelham, 1774-1839. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1838 Jan 26 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    Letter discusses Pettigrew's Medical Portrait Gallery.
  - Bridgeman, George Thomas Orlando. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1860 Oct, Dec (Box 2, Folder 74)
    Letters discuss several of Bridgeman's works.
  - Briggs, John Joseph, 1819-1876. 2 ALS to T.J. Pettigrew, 1841, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    Briggs Agrees to subscribe to a work of Pettigrew on Egypt.
  - Bright, Richard, 1789-1858. 7 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1832 Feb (Box 2, Folder 76)
    One letter discusses an outbreak of scarletina in London.
  - Brinckman, Charlotte (Godolphin), lady, d. 1838. AL to T. J. Pettigrew, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 77)
    Letter discusses a trip by the British Archaeological Association.
  - Britton, John, 1771-1857. 4 ALS and 1 ALS fragment to T.J. Pettigrew, 1846-56 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Brockett, John Trotter, 1788-1842. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1827 Mar 14 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    Brockett seeks permission to send a copy of the second edition of the Glossary of North Country Words in Use to the Duke of Sussex.
  - Brodie, Sir Benjamin Collins, bart., 1783-1862. 14 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1824-[43] (Box 2, Folder 80)
    Letters indicate that Brodie and Pettigrew were good friends. They may have consulted each other about medical problems.
  - Brooke, Richard, 1791-1861. 3 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1852 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 81)
    Letter discusses Pettigrew's apparent resignation from the Society of Antiquaries.
  - Brookes, Joshua, 1761-1833. 3 ALS and 2 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1822-30 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    Includes a testimonial recommending Pettigrew for the post of surgeon at the Bethlehem and Bridewell Hospitals. The last letter mentions Brooke's stay in Hanover, Germany.
  - Brougham, Henry Brougham, 1st Baron, 1778-1868. ALS and AL to T. J. Pettigrew (Box 2, Folder 83)
    Presents a copy of a book with music by W. Linley to the Duke of Sussex.
  - Brown, James, 1812-1881. AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1854 Jul 30 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    Discusses a Congress of the British Archaeological Association.
  - Brownlow, Emma Sophia (Edgcumbe), Countess, 1791-1872. 2 AL to Dr. Sigmond and T. J. Pettigrew, and 1 AL to Pettigrew., [1834 or later] (Box 2, Folder 85)
    Letters regard Brownlow's patronage of an upcoming ball.
  - Bruce, John Collingwood, 1805-1892. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1850 Jun, Sep (Box 2, Folder 86)
    Letter discusses Bruce's work on the Roman Walls in England and other scholarly works.
  - Buckland, William, 1784-1856. 4 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1848-49 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    Letters discuss the creation of a medal honoring Robert Vernon.
  - Burges, George, 1786?-1864. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, [before 1835] (Box 2, Folder 88)
    Announces the beginning of Burges's career as a lecturer and suggests he used to be a tailor. Seeks Pettigrew's support in gaining a large audience for his lectures. Includes a printed prospectus for his lectures.
  - Burgon, Thomas, 1787-1858. 2 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1834, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    Discusses Pettigrew's work on mummies.
  - Burke, Sir John Bernard, 1814-1892. 5 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1853-58 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    Says he is unable to continue to subscribe to the British Archaeological Association and all local Irish organizations to which he feels he should subscribe.
  - Burlington, Elizabeth (Compton) Cavendish, Countess of, 1760-1835. AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1830 Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    Seeks information about the Duke of Sussex's vote for a charity case.
  - Burnett, Gilbert Thomas, 1800-1835. 2 ALS and 1 AL to T. J. Pettigrew, 1831-35 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    One letter discusses the Medico-Botanical Society.
  - Burns, J. ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 93)
    Docketed in unknown hand "Captn Burns Son of Burns the Poet."
  - Caley, John, d. 1834. 3 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1824-33 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Camden, George Charles Pratt, 2d Marquis of, 1799-1866. 3 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1853 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 95)
    Declines the post of President of the British Archaeological Association, but accepts one of many Vice-Presidencies of the association.
  - Carlisle, Sir Anthony, 1768-1840. 4 ALS to T. J. Pettigrew, 1823-38 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    Carlisle criticizes the Royal Society of the Arts and suggests some improvements. He also comments on his brother's involvement in the controversy surrounding Benedetto Pistrucci.